Good morning. Today is June 12th, it's the 18th of סיון. Sivan.
Today's דף daf is going to be בבא בתרא קמ"א Bava Batra
Kuf Mem Aleph 141 and we're going to start picking up right
after the משנה Mishnah on ק"מ עמוד ב'. Kuf Mem Amud Bet.
Rabbi Linzer said that you had learned the משנה Mishnah yesterday. This
is Dan Margulies filling in for Rabbi Linzer
and the משנה Mishnah where we have now just gotten our start
in the ninth פרק, Perek, פרק מי שמת Perek Mi Shemet and
the discussion here in our משנה Mishnah is as follows: הניח בנים
ובנות inniach banim uvanot in a case where someone leaves both male
and female heirs, male and female children, וטומטום veTumtum and the טומטום.
Tumtum. Now generally the halakhic system because it works within a rigid
gender binary and people don't necessarily or I should say external sexual
characteristics don't always fit a binary, so there are halakhic categories for
people known under two categories: there is טומטום Tumtum and there is
אנדרוגינוס. Androgynous. טומטום Tumtum generally we assume refers to someone with what
we might say ambiguous genitalia, and אנדרוגינוס Androgynous refers to a case
where someone presents with both types of sexual characteristic
genitalia. So in this case at least there's going to be some
question about what the opinion is about the halakhic status of טומטום.
Tumtum. Generally we say that each of them is considered to be
a ספק זכר ספק נקבה, safek zachar safek nekevah, but nonetheless the
nature of that ספק safek is different because a טומטום Tumtum in
general is understood to be a ספק בחסרון ידיעה, safek bechesron yediah,
a ספק safek about which we are lacking information which we could
clarify or expand our knowledge through some later event, which the גמרא
Gemara discusses extensively. But אנדרוגינוס Androgynous is usually understood to be a
class ספק, safek, that is every person who falls into that category
is by nature or by definition ספק safek as to whether they're
male or female, so that has different ramifications. טומטום Tumtum is case
by case and אנדרוגינוס Androgynous is by a whole class and there
are other נפקא מינה nafkaminas as well, but that's sort of the
conclusion. The סוגיא sugya at least in the גמרא Gemara deal with
it a lot, have to flesh it out and do a lot
of that work, and even in the ראשונים Rishonim there's a lot
of further elaboration and clarification about that. But the משנה Mishnah had
said הניח בנים ובנות וטומטום, inniach banim uvanot veTumtum, בזמן שהנכסים מרובין,
bizman shehanechasim merubin, the first משנה Mishnah had already discussed this that
in cases where there is a large enough estate to support the
מזונות mizonot for the daughters plus to provide inheritance for the sons,
then we have more room to go with and that's what's called
נכסים מרובין nechasim merubin or ירושה גדולה yerusha gedolah and things like
that. So בזמן שהנכסים מרובין הזכרים דוחים אותו אצל נקבות. bizman shehanechasim
merubin hazekarim dochin oto etzel nekevot. If there is a large estate
that is, the sons want to be able to have their fair
share of the inheritance, the sons can push the טומטום Tumtum child
off to the daughters. In a case נכסים מועטין הנקבות דוחות אותו
אצל זכרים. nechasim muatin hanekevot dochot oto etzel zekarim. In a case
where there is a small estate where the only thing that's going
to be provided is מזונות mizonot for the daughters and there's not
enough to provide inheritance for the sons, then the daughters push off
the טומטום Tumtum to the sons. That is because a טומטום Tumtum
is a case of ספק, safek,
I'm realizing the implication, so
because the טומטום Tumtum is a case of ספק, safek, a case
of doubt, that neither the sons nor the daughters want the טומטום
Tumtum to be counted among their number because that will reduce their
own share of the inheritance.
Okay, in a sense because of the
because of the gender dynamics of the inheritance, someone with an uncertain
gender identity becomes very complicated how to resolve with his brothers and
sisters. So that becomes the challenge of this משנה, Mishnah, and because
we have rules for ממון המוטל בספק, mamon hamutal besafek, there's money
that's in a doubtful situation, either we divide it or you have
to bring proof and different things, so that's going to what part
of what plays out here as well. The second half of the
משנה Mishnah deals with a slightly different case האומר. Haomer. Now the
what? I see what you did there.
I know, I know, I just want to catch up, I have
to learn it you know.
Mr. Guttman, we give you one last chance to wish you מזל
טוב mazel tov on the dinner last night.
Okay, so you did the משנה Mishnah yesterday, I just wanted to
touch on that because we're going to now see the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara says דוחים אותו ושקיל כבת. dochin oto veshakil kebat.
So what do you what does it mean? If they push him
off then what does it mean that he can the טומטום Tumtum
will claim a portion among the daughters? הא קתני סיפא haktani seifa
ילדה טומטום אינו נוטל. yaldah tumtum eino notel. But the סיפא seifa
in the משנה Mishnah says if the child born is a טומטום,
Tumtum, אינו נוטל eino notel in a case where the father had
declared, in a case where I have a son then pay this
much money and if I have a daughter pay this much money,
but טומטום tumtum אינו נוטל. eino notel. can't claim anything because טומטום
tumtum is ספק זכר ספק נקבה, safeik zachar safeik nekeivah, can't make
a positive claim on being either male or female. So in that
case, how can it be? So the question is does the טומטום,
tumtum, why is it that the sons can push the טומטום tumtum
off to the daughters in the רישא, reisha, but in the סיפא,
seifa, the טומטום tumtum can't claim anything? אמר אביי, amar Abaye, דוחו
אותו ואין לו. dochino oto ve-ein lo. It means דוחו אותו, dochino
oto, they push him off and he doesn't get to claim anything
even from the daughters. That is the sons can push him off
אצל נקבות. etzel nekeivot. The sons can say, "You are not male,
you're female." The daughters will say, "You're not female, you're male," and
he'll get nothing. So that's really what it means דוחו אותו. dochino
oto. It's not דוחו אותו אצל נקבות, dochino oto etzel nekeivot, it's
דוחו אותו אצל נקבות dochino oto etzel nekeivot and the נקבות nekeivot
will push him off as well.
That doesn't seem fair, meaning like, you know, he should be entitled
to some sort of support, as an heir then as a daughter.
So
presumably exactly. So רבא Rava disagrees with אביי, Abaye, ורבא אמר דוחו
אותו ויש לו. ve-Rava amar dochino oto ve-yeish lo. רבא Rava says
דוחו אותו dochino oto means he does get some kind of a
claim as Michael suggests because ממה נפשך, miman nafshach, one way or
another he should have some sort of a claim on the inheritance,
either as a son or as a daughter. A doubtful case still
doesn't mean you get nothing.
And so that's רבא's Rava objection to אביי. Abaye. Now אביי's Abaye
point is to say in any situation because either claim is a
doubtful claim and we never are going to give over someone else's
money because of a doubtful claim, so it really gets us into
the question of how do we see the inheritance of a טומטום.
tumtum. Is it that any case of inheritance a child will get
something and then we have to say well which type of child
is this, is it a male child or a female child, or
do we say no, the first question is is it a male
child or female child and the determination of what inheritance they get
only comes after that assessment. So if it's the first one אביי's
Abaye explanation doesn't make any sense because you could say ממה נפשך,
miman nafshach, one way or another he should get something, but if
אביי Abaye is saying you have to be able to claim either
a son status or a daughter status initially, the טומטום tumtum cannot
make a positive determination either way.
So it's just a really you know giving him something,
the דוחו אותו ואין לו. dochino oto ve-ein lo. So the way
to solve it would be for the father to designate some properties
to go to this child. I could imagine that there was a
social stigma against such a child at this time. One of the
unique characteristics of Jewish society as opposed to Greco-Roman society probably was
that Jewish society still encouraged the parents to care for and raise
and love such a child nonetheless. The Greco-Roman society was very fond
of exposing children they determined to be born with some sort of
defect. So of all things to see that this child is grown
up and is in a place to inherit is a positive thing
for us and we have to think about then what's the next
step moving forward. Okay. Okay so אביי Abaye says דוחו אותו ואין
לו, dochino oto ve-ein lo, רבא Rava says דוחו אותו ויש לו.
dochino oto ve-yeish lo. וסיפא אתאן לרבן שמעון בן גמליאל. ve-seifa atan
le-Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel.
Maybe the סיפא seifa fits the position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל,
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, דתנן de-tnan ילדה טומטום ואנדרוגינוס, yaldah tumtum ve-androgynos,
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר אין קדושה חלה עליהם. Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer ein kedusha chala aleihem.
In a context of קרבנות, korbanot, suppose a person has a pregnant
cow and the person says if the animal born is a male
calf I'll bring it as a קרבן עולה korban olah and if
the animal born is a female calf I'll bring it as a
קרבן שלמים. korban shelamim. And what if the animal born is not
able to be determined whether it's male or female but it's either
a טומטום tumtum or אנדרוגינוס? androgynos? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says אין קדושה חלה עליהם. ein kedusha chala aleihem. There's
no designation of קדושה kedusha at all. That is, it's not enough
to say oh, meaning we don't only say we don't know which
one it is but we know it has קדושה kedusha and it
will be a קרבן, korban, but because the determination, the first question
has to be male or female and the second question will then
be well if male then עולה olah and if female then שלמים,
shelamim, so then if you can't make a positive determination of either
male or female that would follow regarding that, so that means רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל's Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel position seems to fit better
with אביי Abaye than with רבא Rava and seems to fit the
סיפא seifa which was the proof for אביי. Abaye.
Okay. מיתיבי, meitivei, טומטום יורש כבן, tumtum yoreish ke-ven, but we have
a contradictory ברייתא braisa because a ברייתא braisa suggests טומטום יורש כבן
tumtum yoreish ke-ven that a טומטום tumtum could inherit like a son,
that is counted among the sons, וניזון כבת ve-nizon ke-bat and receives
מזונות mezonot like a daughter, that is both in fact, not that
the טומטום. tumtum. Ah, so it also seems unfair because that way
he gets more inheritance. So either way a doubtful case is going
to be problematic. Either we have to make some sort of a
determination one way or the other or we have to say neither
or we have to say both. Neither doesn't seem very fair. fair,
both doesn't seem very fair, and we really can't resolve the determination
any clear way either. So we're still stuck. But this ברייתא baraita
at least suggests a different possibility, that is not seeing it as,
well, a ספק safek you can't claim anything, but actually ספק safek
gives you the legs to claim both. In a sense, we could
understand that the ספק safek inherent in טומטום tumtum according to that
ברייתא baraita's position is a very strong ספק. safek. You say ספק
זכר ספק נקבה, safek zachar safek nekevah, that's actually almost a hundred
percent of both in a sense, and that would motivate the ability
to be יורש כבן וניזון כבת. yoresh ke-ben ve-nizon ke-bat. So the
גמרא Gemara asks: בשלמא לרבא bishlama le-Rava that—that ברייתא baraita fits relatively
well according to רבא Rava who said יורש כבן בנכסים מועטים. yoresh
ke-ben be-nechasim muatim. In a case where there are few properties, he's
יורש כבן yoresh ke-ben means he doesn't get anything. So they'll read
it backwards, right? The ברייתא baraita sounds like it says יורש כבן
yoresh ke-ben he does get the inheritance and וניזון כבת ve-nizon ke-bat
he does get the מזונות, mezonot, but רבא Rava said דוחנין אותו
ביש לו dochinin oto be-yesh lo that the son can push him
off and he can claim מזונות. mezonot. So רבא Rava said יורש
כבן yoresh ke-ben בנכסים מועטים. be-nechasim muatim. He gets a male's inheritance
when there's a small estate. That means most of the property's going
to go to the daughters for their מזונות mezonot and the properties
for the son will be relatively small, or nonexistent. וניזון כבת בנכסים
מרובים, ve-nizon ke-bat be-nechasim merubim, and a case where there's a large
estate and a son would get a substantial portion, then he only
gets ניזון כבת, nizon ke-bat, he only gets מזונות. mezonot. So he
gets the smaller possibility. That's a sort of a ממה נפשך. mimah
nafshach. It's like, either he's male or female, so we'll give him
whichever claim is the lesser claim. It's kind of like the way
to resolve this problem is give him something, but not—I keep saying
him, but the whole point is that it's someone who has an
ambiguous gender.
Okay. וניזון כבת בנכסים מרובים ve-nizon ke-bat be-nechasim merubim is willing to
sort of
right. The משנה Mishnah on the one hand and the ברייתא baraita
right. Through the lens of רבא Rava we prefer רבא Rava generally,
and we prefer the position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel in the משנה Mishnah in—I think it's in ערכין, Arachin,
is that right?
No, it's in תמורה. Temurah.
We usually פוסקין paskin like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel, and we usually like רבא, Rava, so we want to fit
them both together and we want it to fit our משנה Mishnah
and we want it to fit this other ברייתא. baraita. So we're
kind of mushing it together. The idea here basically: give him the
weaker claim, give the טומטום tumtum the weaker claim, but it's enough
to resolve—resolve the situation. אלא לאביי, ela le-Abaye, the גמרא Gemara continues,
but what about אביי Abaye's position? Yeah, David, you have a question?
Yeah, just to say that the insertion here of רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel's opinion about the sacrifice, it's like giving
it a—a metaphysical quality it doesn't have any sanctity. Right,
they—they kind of judging the human being in terms
of—I don't think that's the sense. The sense is when you're מקדיש
makdish an animal to be a קרבן, korban, does that קדושה kedusha
take hold in the case of if you said: if it's male
then it's this and if it's female then it's this, and you
have a calf is a טומטום, tumtum, it means it doesn't fit
into either category.
Right, but in a sense
it's like it's justifying what we're just up to the decision of
saying that he doesn't—he's gonna—Maybe,
I would—I'm not sure I would read it that far. All right.
What would they do if this was like a בכור? bechor?
Right, so in the case of בכור, bechor, exactly, there—well, that's why
it comes up, this discussion there in בכור bechor and the discussion
here about—about the children as well, if the first child born is
a טומטום tumtum or אנדרוגינוס androgynos you get into some complex questions
about בכור. bechor.
In some ways the safest way is like, you know, you're מקדיש
makdish whatever this animal's—is and just—say, all right, whatever it is, I'm
מקדיש makdish it as a שלמים shelamim maybe.
Well, because sometimes people don't want to do that. Sometimes an עולה
olah is a higher קדושה, kedusha, right? Anyway, אלא לאביי, ela le-Abaye,
so we go right on the top of קמ ע"א, Kuf Mem
Amud Aleph, אלא לאביי, ela le-Abaye, אביי, Abaye, what about אביי Abaye's
position? Because אביי Abaye had said דוחנין אותו ואין לו. dochinin oto
ve-ein lo. The טומטום tumtum can claim neither מזונות mezonot nor ירושה.
yerusha. So if the טומטום tumtum can claim neither, then how does
that fit with the position of רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel and how does that fit with the ברייתא baraita that
says יורש כבן וניזון כבת? yoresh ke-ben ve-nizon ke-bat? So אלא לאביי
מאי ניזון כבת? ela le-Abaye mai nizon ke-bat? What does it mean
that a טומטום tumtum would get מזונות mezonot like—like a daughter? ולטעמך,
u-le-taamecha, so it fits his own position. לרבא מאי יורש כבן? le-Rava
mai yoresh ke-ben? And for רבא, Rava, what does it mean that
he'll be able to claim an inheritance like a son? אלא ראוי
לירש ואין לו. ela raui leresh ve-ein lo. Really, the reason he's
not able—he's put into the son's category to get him out of
the daughter's category, but then also can't inherit with the sons. הכא
נמי ראוי לזון ואין לו hacha nami raui lazon ve-ein lo would
be fitting, would be suitable to put into the daughter's category to
get מזונות, mezonot, ואין לו, ve-ein lo, and also doesn't get. That
is, according to אביי, Abaye, either way, you can't—you're pushed out of
one category but he doesn't have enough claim to get into the
other category, and that's why
ואין לו.
ve-ein lo. He simply, basically, interpreted it to its opposite.
So right, we took the ברייתא braita and because
the גמרא Gemara means neither, really.
Right, because we wanted the ברייתא braita to fit with the positions
of the אמוראים, Amoraim, we have to read the ברייתא braita in
a way that maybe is not פשט pshat in the ברייתא. braita.
Again, ברייתות braitot aren't always so authoritative. So you have a text
of the ברייתא braita you want to claim it as authoritative. So
often the way of rejecting the ברייתא braita is a way to
be re-reading the ברייתא. braita. That's just the mechanism. Yeah.
Does this particular ברייתא braita appear in the תוספתא? Tosefta?
I could not tell you right now, I would have to go
check.
My guess is no, just because I don't see any citation. Maybe,
it depends. It's all, we have good ברייתות braitot and we have
bad ברייתות braitot and we have ברייתות braitot that just have rejected
positions and we have all sorts of things. Okay, we're on the
third line of קמ"א Kuf Mem Aleph and the גמרא Gemara is
now going to continue with the discussion, we're going to go on
a bit of a tangent which is about whether in Talmudic times
it was seen as better or worse to have a boy first
or a daughter first.
Obviously it's tied up a lot with the gender norms of that
society and cultural expectations and all sorts of things,
and particular because in the משנה Mishna the suggestion was האומר אם
תלד אשתי זכר יטול מנה, ha-omer im teled ishti zachar yitol maneh,
if my wife gives birth to a son he should take 100,
100 זוז, zuz, 25 זוז, zuz, ילדה זכר יטול מנה yalda zachar
yitol maneh and the נקבה מאתים. nekeva matayim. So the point is
that the משנה Mishna has suggested giving out a double, a double
baby baby gift for a daughter than for a son.
Well yeah because the daughters, you know, aren't able to go out
and get a job.
Well the גמרא's Gemara suggestion לממרא דבת עדיפא lememra de-bat adifa that
בת עדיפא ליה מבן. bat adifa leh mi-ben. So the גמרא's Gemara
suggestion is actually that maybe the father actually prefers to have a
daughter rather than a son. Okay, but that seems at least a
bit surprising to the גמרא Gemara והאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון
בן יוחי. ve-ha-amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. So רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said quoting רבי שמעון בן יוחי Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai כל שאינו מניח בן ליורשו הקדוש ברוך הוא מלא עליו עברה.
kol she-eino maniach ben le-yorsho ha-kadosh baruch hu malei alav evrah. עברה.
evrah.
עברה. evrah. עברה. evrah. Okay, עברה, evrah, right, okay. Is that from
the right פסוק pasuk יום עברה? yom evrah? Okay, so God is
angry at you if you don't leave over anger.
So if you don't leave over a son to be able to
inherit your property, God will be angry at you דכתיב והעברתם את
נחלתו לבתו. dichtiv ve-ha-avartem et nachalato le-vito. You have to transfer the
property, the inheritance to the daughter ואין העברה אלא עברה. ve-ein ha-avara
ela evra. העברה ha-avara transferring over really refers to to anger. We
saw this referenced briefly a few weeks ago I think like three
weeks ago שנאמר יום עברה היום ההוא. shene'emar yom evrah ha-yom ha-hu.
So
יום עברה היום. yom evrah ha-yom. So from צפניה, Tzefanya, צפניה Tzefanya
is not a particularly cheery book of נבואה nevuah which is why
none of our הפטרות haftarot are taken from it. It's very, very
bleak. But
so this suggestion is that now obviously you can understand it just
to mean oh whoever first of all, right for a man the
מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו peru u-revu is to have a son
and a daughter or according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai two sons.
So obviously already there's some expectation to be to be leaving over
a male heir, at least that's sort of the hope of the
מצוה. mitzvah. At the same time, here there's a denigration of what
it would mean to only have daughters or to only have, you
know, one daughter or something like that, and that seems to contradict
the statement in this משנה Mishna which at least supposes that the
father would be happier or more excited to learn about the birth
of a daughter.
Not necessarily, I mean like he mentions also son first האומר אם
תלד
אשתי זכר.
ha-omer im
teled ishti zachar.
He mentioned the son first but he gives a double, a double
payment for the daughter. Okay. So okay anyway, so we're going to
see why. So ההוא לענין ירושה ha-hu le-inyan yerusha so בן עדיף
ליה. ben adif leh. It's better to have a son regarding inheritance
because the son's inheritance has a stronger sense. We saw the...
Plus he stays in the family.
He stays in the family more. There's a discussion of בן כרעא
דאבוה ben karea de-avuh
the son fills the role, fills in the shoes of the father
rather than just inheriting from the father, maybe there's even a qualitative
difference in how the inheritance works. However לענין הרוחה בתו עדיפא ליה.
le-inyan harvacha bito adifa leh. But in terms of הרוחה harvacha like
gains,
profitable gains, a daughter is better.
Maybe like in commerce?
It's not so clear what they what they mean.
רשב"ם Rashbam says בתו עדיפא bito adifa שאינה יכולה לחזור אחר מזונותיה
כזכר. she-eina yechola lachzor achar mezonoteha ke-zachar. The claims of the מזונות
mezonot are actually a weaker, weaker claims on the inheritance but there
it doesn't make sense because there, because first of all, because if
also because the daughter would be inheriting, if there are no sons
the daughter would inherit the whole property.
So I don't exactly understand what he means לענין הרוחה le-inyan harvacha
whatever הרוחה harvacha this is some kind of investment.
What about the ArtScroll?
David what does the ArtScroll suggest? Any helpful suggestions?
Something through ample provision in daughters preferred by him than the other.
Yeah, the רשב"ם Rashbam says it has to do with מזונות, mezonot,
but I just don't understand the mechanism. The רשב"ם'ס Rashbam's mechanism seems
a bit strange. Well,
when
it comes to provide for children, he prefers to make ample provisions
for his daughters because they are less able than the sons.
Ah, maybe Michael, this is what you're suggesting, that the making a
gift at hearing the news of the birth of the daughter would
be a reason to give her a larger gift, on her, you
know, buy her some bonds, because she won't be able to support
herself as much later, so provide for her more now, perhaps. Okay,
ושמואל אמר הכא במבכרת עסקינן. ushmuel amar hacha bemivakeret askinan. No,
שמואל Shmuel says our משנה mishna is dealing with a case of
someone giving birth to her first child. וכדרב חסדא דאמר רב חסדא,
ukiderav Chisda deamar Rav Chisda, בת תחילה סימנא יפה לבנים. bat techila
simanya yafeh labanim.
רב חסדא Rav Chisda said if you have a daughter first, it's
a good sign for later children. Why?
Would it be like male children, meaning like more big, more sons
ultimately come out ahead because you get...
So we have two different possibilities. איכא דאמרי דמרבי לאחיה. ika deamrei
demarbei leachacha.
One position understands that to mean that a daughter who is the
eldest child will be able to raise her younger brothers, she'll be
able to help her mother in raising the children.
Okay. מרביא, marbeia, it means raising.
מרביא, marbeia, right, like to, like, like רביא, rabia, like to increase.
פרו ורבו pru urevu doesn't necessarily mean to have more kids, it
means to raise them in a certain way.
Right, to raise them. Right. So the eldest child, we know, fits
into some of the מצוות mitzvot of כיבוד אב ואם, kibbud av
va'em, that there's a sense that the eldest child has a חיוב,
chiyuv, the younger children have to show their elder siblings some amount
of כיבוד, kibbud, in a parallel to the parent. So there's some
sense of that as well. So here, if you have a daughter
first, the eldest daughter will be able to raise the children with
her mother better. דאיכא דאמרי דלא שלטה בה עינא בישא. deika deamrei
delo shalta bah eina bisha. And some people say there's no עין
הרע ayin hara or there's less עין הרע ayin hara when a
daughter is born first. It may have something to do with the...
that they had a boy, everyone is like oh wow,
so now they have a girl, oh. Right, so maybe something like
that, or maybe something to do with the עין הרע ayin hara
associated with ברית מילה, brit milah, that
undergoing any kind of a surgical procedure, there's a fear of עין
הרע, ayin hara, and certainly around the ברית מילה brit milah there's
a sense of demons and all sorts of things, that's where a
lot of kabbalistic customs of the ברית brit developed.
So either way, those are two interpretations of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda.
So אמר רב חסדא ולדידי, amar Rav Chisda uledidi, בנתן עדיפן לי
מבנאי. binatan adifan li mibanai. And רב חסדא Rav Chisda said my
daughters are better for me than my sons.
Do you have any sons?
It's not clear. I don't remember the whole story here. I think
one interpretation that I saw when I was preparing this was just
the suggestion that because רב חסדא Rav Chisda may have had two
wives, and if you have two wives, whichever wife gives birth first
and has a son is going to cause more jealousy among the
wives. If they have a daughter, there'll be less jealousy because in
this society there... So it's a catch-22. Because daughters are less desirable
in this society, then having a daughter first will reduce the jealousy,
so it means daughters are more preferable. It's like kind of circular.
There's also another note here. Okay, what... תוספות Tosafot says that because
there won't be a double inheritance.
Right, so there won't
be infighting among the siblings.
Right, if there's no, if no child is designated as the בכור
bechor because a daughter is born first, then even the later sons
will have an easier time dividing the inheritance.
He might have been saying what I was saying, you didn't have
to argue about this second marriage when you have... לא נתקיימו ליה
בנין. lo nikayemu lei banin.
So
maybe he had sons and they didn't survive to adulthood, which would
also be tragic and was very common back then. Okay. So okay,
ואיבעית אימא הא מני רבי יהודה היא. ve'iba'it eima ha mani rabbi
yehudah hi. So, and so we can ask, that is, who is
our משנה mishna like? That is, the whole discussion so far was
our משנה mishna is like רב חסדא Rav Chisda in that it
seems to... having a daughter is better and is not like רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So who is our משנה? mishna? הא מני רבי
יהודה היא. ha mani rabbi yehudah hi. Maybe it's רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. So היי רבי יהודה, hai rabbi yehudah, is it really רבי
יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? אילימא רבי יהודה דבכל, ileima rabbi yehudah debakol, so
which רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? What are we talking about? It's a
מדרש midrash on the פסוק pasuk that at the end of אברהם'ס
Abraham's life, ויי ברך את אברהם בכל. vadonai berach et avraham bakol.
God blessed אברהם Abraham with everything. We mention it in בענטשין, benching,
in ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon, we reference three different פסוקים psukim about
אברהם, Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, and יעקב, Yaakov, we say בכל מכל כל.
bakol mikol kol. Each of them was blessed in one way or
another, they declared their ברכות brachot from God. So in this case,
for אברהם, Abraham, is blessed with the word בכל. bakol. So here
we have a מחלוקת תנאים machloket tanaim about what does that mean?
Okay, so אילימא רבי יהודה דבכל, ileima rabbi yehudah debakol, it's the
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of בכל. bakol. דתניא, detanya, this is the
ברייתא, baraita, ויי ברך את אברהם בכל, vadonai berach et avraham bakol,
God blessed אברהם Abraham with everything, רבי מאיר אומר שלא היה לו
בת. Rabbi Meir omer shelo hayah lo bat. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says the blessing that אברהם Abraham received was to not have a
daughter.
רבי יהודה אומר שהיתה לו בת ובכל שמה. Rabbi Yehuda omer shehayetah
lo bat uvakol shemah. says the ברכה berachah was that he did
have a daughter and that her name was בכל, Bakol, which is
kind of an odd name for a daughter, but nonetheless,
the מחלוקת machloket at least between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about whether having a daughter is beneficial or detrimental,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir sees it as more detrimental and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda sees it as more beneficial.
Rabbi Linder tells a joke on that one. What's the joke? The
joke is what was he so worried about? ונוח V'Noach can marry
you, כוש Cush can marry you. So what was he worried about
going all the way to...
oh that יצחק Yitzchak would be able to marry her.
So it was why did you say okay, marry the daughter of
בכל? Bakol? The answer is because he wanted his daughter to marry
a real person, not a מדרש. midrash.
He wanted יצחק Yitzchak to marry a real person.
That's a cute joke. I like that joke. I keep a good
record of Rabbi Linder's jokes, so I'll have to add this one
to the...
The way רב הירש Rav Hirsch explains this, how can it be
a blessing not to have a daughter? What he said is given
how worried he was...
It was a concern about marrying her...
More worried he would be if he had a daughter and the
daughter would go live with the
idolatrous in-laws. Of course.
So
and some people have suggested that I remember this was a more
recent suggestion, it's worth exploring more, but that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
of all the תנאים Tannaim has a certain amount of more misogynistic
comments than other תנאים Tannaim perhaps, so there's something worth צריך עיון
tsarich iyun about that.
It's by the fact or maybe because,
because his wife was ברוריה. Beruriah. A daughter of... Exactly. Okay. So
אימר דשמעת ליה לרבי יהודה ברתא נמי לא חסרה רחמנא לאברהם, Eimar
dishmiat lei leRabbi Yehuda barta nami lo chasera Rachmana l'Avraham,
so
fine, you can understand רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying that it's a
ברכה berachah for אברהם Avraham that God did not deny him anything,
that God blessed him with something of everything in this world, including
having a daughter, but דעדיפא מבן מי שמעת ליה? d'adifa miben mi
shmiat lei? Who ever heard you can't extrapolate from רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda position that having a daughter is better than having a son?
You could say that having a daughter is a wonderful thing, that's
an important part of life and it was something that God wanted
to bless
אברהם Avraham with, but it's not evident from רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda
position that he could be the one who thinks having a daughter
is better. רב חסדא Rav Chisda still does. Okay. אלא הא רבי
יהודה, ella ha Rabbi Yehuda, it must be a different opinion of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that demonstrates that logically. That is, the ברייתא
baraita of בכל Bakol doesn't prove that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks
having a daughter is better, but this ברייתא baraita says
what? דתניא מצוה לזון את הבנות וקל וחומר לבנים דעסקי בתורה דברי
רבי מאיר. D'tanya mitzvah l'zon et habanot v'kal vachomer l'banim d'aski baTorah
divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that there's a קל
וחומר kal vachomer one should provide financial support for one's sons who
are studying תורה. Torah. The daughters didn't study תורה Torah then, the
sons did. So if you're studying תורה, Torah, of course you deserve
some financial support.
ורבי יהודה אומר מצוה לזון את הבנים וקל וחומר לבנות דלא ליזלן.
VeRabbi Yehuda omer mitzvah l'zon et habanim v'kal vachomer l'banot d'lo litzalan.
And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says there's a מצוה mitzvah to provide
support for the sons and קל וחומר kal vachomer for the daughters
to prevent them from falling into
דלא ליזלן lo litzalan that they shouldn't become disgraced, become cheapened in
that they would have to, either whatever way they would have to
support themselves might not be fitting for their family or for their
class standing.
Yes, those two last words though are not part of the ברייתא,
baraita, correct?
דלא ליזלן D'lo litzalan is my assumption. Exactly, right, because it's an
Aramaic appendage,
it's
a gloss explaining why רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks the קל וחומר
kal vachomer is לבנות. l'banot. In fact, even דעסקי בתורה d'aski baTorah
is probably not necessarily
דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. Right, it's very sneaky. Often you
find these ברייתות baraitot that have Aramaic glosses
interpolated inside the text of the ברייתא. baraita.
Okay. אלא, Ella, so that suggests that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks
having a daughter is perhaps in some way better than a son
because there's a קל וחומר kal vachomer to support the daughters. אלא
הא דתניא ילדה זכר
ונקבה הזכר נוטל ששה דינרים והנקבה נוטלת שני דינרים.
Ella ha d'tanya yalda zachar
u'nekeiva, hazachar notel shisha dinarim v'hanekeiva notelat shnei dinarim. So a different
version of the same case that appears in our משנה. mishnah.
Yeah.
Same words, kind of substituted for... this is a good proof that...
that's a good proof that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks there's more
reason to celebrate the birth of a daughter than...
דלא ליזלן d'lo litzalan and that...
Right. So he sees it as inherently some kind of a practical
benefit or practical need, but it's at least the assumption or the
argument that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda sees a קל וחומר kal vachomer
from בנים banim to בנות banot preferences the בנות banot in some
way.
Nonetheless, so that means our משנה mishnah perhaps is the opinion of
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. The best claim we could have come up
with is that it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but we have a
ברייתא baraita that illustrates the same case as the משנה, mishnah, but
rather than putting the daughter preferential treatment, gives the son preferential treatment.
אלא הא דתניא... Ella ha d'tanya... ברייתא, braita, ילדה זכר ונקבה, yalda
zachar unekeivah, הזכר נוטל ששה דינרים, hazachar notel shisha dinarim, in a
case where the woman gives birth to twins, a boy and a
girl, the son gets six דינרים dinarim and the daughter gets two
דינרים. dinarim. So in that ברייתא braita you see the son gets
three times what the daughter
gets, is indication that the תנא tanna of the ברייתא braita chose
a different case to illustrate the same הלכה halacha because he disagreed
with the תנא tanna of the משנה mishnah about the preferential standing
of daughters. That is, the משנה mishnah sees daughters as preferential and
the ברייתא braita sees the sons as preferential. במאי? Bemai? אמר רב
אשי, amar Rav Ashi, אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב כהנא. amritah lishmata kammai
deRav Kahana. So רב אשי Rav Ashi says, "I was saying over
this whole שיעור shiur by רב כהנא," Rav Kahana, and he said,
"במסרס, bimsares, דאמר זכר תחילה מאתיים." deamar zachar techilla masayim. So you
have to like smush it around. מסרס Msares here about מסרס שסירס
תנאיו. msares sheseres tana'av. He spliced together the different conditions of this
deal that he was making. רש"י Rashi often says סרסהו. sarsehu. לסרס
Lesares obviously means to sterilize someone, but in the context of the
grammatically, move the words around. Exactly. Reword them in syntactic order. Re-splice
the phrases of the claim. So רב אשי Rav Ashi says, "I
was saying this this שיעור shiur over to רב כהנא," Rav Kahana,
and he said, "במסרס. bimsares. That what I explained the case as
is someone who flipped around the phrases of the תנאי. tnai. דאמר,
Deamar,
זכר תחילה מאתיים. zachar techilla masayim. If my wife gives birth to
a boy first, 200. נקבה אחריה ולא כלום. nekeivah achareha velo klum.
And then a daughter comes after, then nothing. נקבה תחילה מנה. nekeivah
techilla maneh. If the daughter is born first, then 100. זכר אחריה
מנה. zachar achareha maneh. And the son afterwards will get 100. וילדה
זכר ונקבה. veyalda zachar unekeivah. And then so what happened? He said,
"If my wife is carrying fraternal twins, a boy and a girl,
if the boy is born first, he'll get 200 and the daughter
gets nothing. If the girl is born first, she gets 100 and
the son gets 100." And then the father is not there for
the delivery, obviously.
And then, obviously that was meant to be a joke.
And then they show up and they say, ילדה זכר ונקבה ולא
ידעינן הי מינייהו נפק ברישא. yalda zachar unekeivah velo yadinan hai mineihu
nafak bereisha. And they don't know which of the two twins was
born first. זכר שקיל מנה ממה נפשך. zachar shakil maneh mimma nafshach.
The son can claim 100 either way, because maybe he was born
first and he's really entitled to 200, or maybe he was born
second and he's entitled to 100. So either way he gets 100
and the daughter gets nothing because either she was born first and
she gets 100 or she was born second and she gets nothing.
So המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. Okay. Perhaps. Or
אידך מנה הוה ממון המוטל בספק וחולקין. idach maneh hava mamon hamutal
besafek vecholkin. Do we so this is an illustration of a case
actually where we go like סומכוס, Sumchus, which is interesting. The last
100 should be split. So the son will get 150 and the
daughter will get 50. והא דתניא ילדה זכר ונקבה אין לו אלא
מנה.
veha detanya yalda zachar unekeivah
ein lo ella maneh. But didn't our משנה mishnah or didn't the
ברייתא braita say if she gave birth to both a boy and
a girl, that the maximum payout will be 100 because he had
explicated that. So היכי משכחת לה? heichi mashkachat lah? What case is
that? That is, if he said, ילדה זכר ונקבה אין לו אלא
מנה. yalda zachar unekeivah ein lo ella maneh. So what case is
that? אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, במבשרני. bimvasreni.
He's talking about who is going the who's getting the money, not
that the children are going to get the money. The person who
brings me the news that my wife just gave birth, that's the
person who's getting the money.
Before we continue, yes. So when we're talking about which money is
this exactly?
This is money that the father wants to give as a gift,
designated according to the birth order of the children.
As a gift upon death?
No, presumably just as
a gift.
A birth gift. Right now, either to the children or, as רבינא
Ravina suggests, to the messenger who brings him the news that his
wife just gave birth.
So so the גמרא's Gemara made a shift... what is?
The משנה mishnah was also talking about this gift?
Yes. The משנה mishnah says האומר אם תלד אשתי זכר יטול מנה.
haomer im teled ishti zachar yitol maneh. So is that שכיב מרע?
shachiv meira? The רשב"ם Rashbam reads it or תוספות, Tosafot, no, it's
תוספות, Tosafot, right? Yeah. The first תוספות Tosafot on קמ"א עמוד ב
kuf mem aleph amud bet says נכסיה דהאי דמיעבר nechasei dehai deme'avar
that this is talking about a case many of these cases are
cases of a שכיב מרע shachiv meira who's designating his inheritance now
how it will be apportioned to the children because the wife is
about to give birth and he wants to say that... that's what
I was looking for. That's at least the next case we're dealing
with, possibly this case as well,
or
it's just a gift in
general. Maybe, right? It's possible it's part of the שכיב מרע shachiv
meira case. It's possible to understand it more broadly. Right. Okay. The
next case is going to be a kind of a שכיב מרע
shachiv meira case and we're and how the סוגיות sugyot are connected
or not is part of the question in the ראשונים. rishonim. So
רבינא... Ravina... Ravina said, Ravina says במבשרני, bimvasrani, whoever informs me of
the news, דתניא, ditanya, so we have a ברייתא braitah that supports
this reading of the משנה: mishna:
המבשרני במה נפטרה רחמה של אשתי, hamvasrani bemah niftarah rachmah shel ishti,
whoever informs me how my wife's the first progeny of my wife's
womb, אם זכר יטול מנה, im zachar yitol maneh, if it's a
boy will get one hundred, ילדה זכר נוטל מנה, yalda zachar notel
maneh, and she gave birth to a boy then he gets one
hundred. That is the messenger will get one hundred.
It's not the only person who's really going to know first is
the midwife.
Right, but then they'll bring someone who sends a telegram to whatever,
you know, like...
But she's not getting anything.
I don't know, I would hope they paid the midwife also.
Yes, but I mean is she getting this מנה? maneh? Right.
Well, unless she's the one who goes and tells the husband.
That's where I was going.
Okay. אם נקבה, im nekeva, and if it's a daughter who's born
מנה, maneh, and he designates one hundred for that, ילדה נקבה נוטל
מנה, yalda nekeva notel maneh, then when a daughter is born he
should get one hundred. ילדה זכר ונקבה אין לו אלא מנה, yalda
zachar unekeva ein lo ela maneh, and if the wife gives birth
to twins, a boy and a girl, still the messenger only gets
one hundred. But what do you mean? והא זכר ונקבה לא אמר?
veha zachar unekeva lo amar? But he didn't even designate that. He
didn't discuss that case. So maybe you should say he shouldn't get
anything at all, or maybe you should say he should get two
hundred because there was both a boy and a girl. So
אלא מנה, ela maneh, he should get
one hundred. והא זכר ונקבה לא אמר דאמר נמי אם זכר ונקבה
נמי יטול מנה. veha zachar unekeva lo amar de'amar nami im zachar
unekeva nami yitol maneh. No, he had explicitly stated: and if it's
twins, a boy and a girl, also will only get one hundred.
So then אלא למעוטי מאי? ela le'ma'uti mai? So what is he
excluding? Meaning you've described every kind of birth possibility: the firstborn is
a boy, the firstborn is a girl, and it's twins, a boy
and a girl. There could be twins two boys or twins two
girls. I don't know about that. But the גמרא Gemara says... so
but in each case the point is that the father has said
the messenger will get one hundred. So what's it to exclude? למעוטי
נפל. le'ma'uti nefel. נפל nefel in a case where there's a miscarriage
or perhaps even in a case where the baby who's born is
not not viable, in such a case the messenger would not get
the payout because presumably it doesn't count, miscarriage doesn't count as something
worthy of the celebration the same way that the birth of a
healthy baby.
If the first birth is a נפל nefel then there's no בכור.
bechor. Right, exactly.
So נפל nefel in some ways does count as a birth for
certain things. It's פטירת רחם, pitrat rechem, it counts as the opening
of the womb for the in terms of birth order, but nonetheless
is not does not designate it either as זכר zachar or נקבה
nekeva in the sense because the נפל nefel is born born without
life. So it doesn't benefit the messenger in that sense, which to
a certain extent makes sense but obviously very tragic circumstance. Okay, the
next case is ההוא דאמר להו לדביתיה נכסאי להאי דמיעברת. hahu de'amar
lehu lediveiteih nechasai lehai demiavrat. So this is a שכיב מרע shechiv
mera case. The husband is on his deathbed, the wife is pregnant,
and the husband says: I designate all the properties to go to
whomever you are pregnant with. Okay, so that's the claim he wants
to make. So אמר רב הונא... amar Rav Huna... oh but what's
the problem is the baby isn't born yet, right? So אמר רב
הונא הוי מזכה לעובר והמזכה לעובר לא קנה. amar Rav Huna havei
mezakeh le'ubar vehamzakeh le'ubar lo kana. According to
רב הונא, Rav Huna, a fetus can't own property. So because the
שכיב מרע shechiv mera is trying to transfer ownership at this time
to a fetus and a fetus can't own anything, it doesn't work.
What does he say exactly? What does he say?
He says דאמר להו
לדביתיה,
de'amar lehu
lediveiteih, to the one of his house, that means the wife. Right,
his
wife. נכסאי להאי דמיעברת. nechasai lehai demiavrat.
I'm giving it to this one with whom
you are pregnant, דמיעברת, demiavrat, right, that you are pregnant with.
So he wants his future child who will be born בשעה טובה
besha'ah tovah to have his properties, but because it's still a fetus,
there's no way for the fetus to own property according to רב
הונא. Rav Huna. So אמר רב הונא האי מזכה לעובר והמזכה לעובר
לא קנה. amar Rav Huna hai mezakeh le'ubar vehamzakeh le'ubar lo kana.
Now you could say that the קנין kinyan was with the woman
because...
oh he could say
with the woman like by proxy. Right. So this formula... she could
have been זוכה. zocha.
We could get into all kinds of questions about עובר ירך אמו,
ubar yerech imo, עובר לאו ירך אמו, ubar lav yerech imo, and
do we say it either way and do we say it for
the... Right, you could get into all kinds of complicated things.
So רב
הונא Rav Huna says an עובר ubar you can't you can't transfer
ownership to an עובר. ubar. Okay, interestingly enough this always comes up
with עובר. ubar. The רמב"ם Rambam talks about a case where a
man goes up to a pregnant woman... goes well, goes up to
the father of a fetus, the husband of a pregnant woman and
says: I want to marry your fetal daughter if it's a daughter
and gives the money. And if the child is born a girl,
technically the קנין kinyan worked for קידושין. kiddushin. Oh. Which goes into
all sorts of strange things. But the רמב"ם Rambam then says another
thing, the רמב"ם Rambam says: but
it's
better to go back and do...
So
it's kind of a strange gray area. Okay, we don't do that
anymore. Okay. אמר רב הונא הוה מזכי ליה עובר מזכי ליה עובר
לא קנה. Amar Rav Huna hava mazkei leh ubar mazkei leh ubar
lo kana. איתיביה רב נחמן לרב הונא. Eitiveia Rav Nachman leRav Huna.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman comes to contradict רב הונא, Rav Huna, quoting
this source. האומר אם ילדה אשתי זכר יטול מנה. Ha'omer im yalda
ishti zachar yitol maneh. If my wife gives birth to a boy,
then he should get 100. ילדה זכר נוטל מנה, Yalda zachar notel
maneh, and she gave birth to a boy, so he gets 100.
אמר ליה
משנתינו איני יודע מי שנה.
Amar leh
mishnateinu eini yodeia mi shan'ah. He said to him, that is, רב
נחמן Rav Nachman said to רב הונא, Rav Huna, I don't know
who taught our משנה. Mishna. So we have to understand what claim
is רב נחמן Rav Nachman bringing from a source? רב הונא Rav
Huna defends himself by saying I don't know who taught our משנה.
Mishna. So what is רב נחמן'ס Rav Nachman's claim from our משנה?
Mishna?
Our משנה Mishna suggests that העובר ha'ubar is זוכה. zocheh.
Right, because if the fetal boy at the time of the condition
the case was I'll give you 100 if you are born a
boy, and then he was born a boy, so then he was
זוכה zocheh back then, so then it's מזכה לעובר. mazkei le'ubar. So
then העובר ha'ubar was זוכה.
zocheh. The son.
Right, this is not like רבינא'ס Ravina's read of the משנה Mishna
where it was the messenger. This is going back to our initial
read of the משנה Mishna that it's about the child acquiring the
money.
In fact, the whole משנה Mishna in a way is predicated on
the assumption that מזכה לעובר.
mazkei le'ubar.
Right, you can be
מזכה mazakeh the
עובר.
ubar. Exactly.
So רב נחמן'ס Rav Nachman's claim is our משנה Mishna is a
proof against רב הונא. Rav Huna. רב הונא'ס Rav Huna's defense is
אמר ליה משנתינו איני יודע מי שנה. Amar leh mishnateinu eini yodeia
mi shan'ah. I don't know who taught our משנה. Mishna. That is,
we already had a debate actually about who was the תנא Tanna
of our משנה. Mishna. Perhaps the תנא Tanna of our משנה Mishna
accords with רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, perhaps does
not accord with רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, מחלוקת
רבא ואביי. machlokes Rava ve'Abaye. Perhaps it's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, perhaps
it's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So there was a whole set of
שיקולים shikulim about which תנא Tanna is it who authored our משנה
Mishna and therefore is the משנה Mishna even authoritative or not. If
רב הונא Rav Huna comes and says yeah, maybe the משנה Mishna
isn't authoritative, maybe the משנה Mishna is a rejected opinion and רב
הונא Rav Huna holds
אי אפשר לזכות לעובר, ee efshar lezakos le'ubar,
אינו מזכה לעובר, eino mazakeh le'ubar, so then it shouldn't be a
problem. ולימא ליה רבי מאיר. Velayma leh Rabbi Meir. Maybe, so now
we're going to go through possibilities of who could have authored the
משנה. Mishna. Again, some of these will be repeats of תנאים Tannaim
we've seen already. And it's going to continue on to tomorrow's דף.
daf. We'll get part of the way there. We'll get to the
bottom
of רב נחמן'ס Rav Nachman's explanation now that we're trying to understand...
Right, that is, רב נחמן Rav Nachman said ah, there's a proof
against רב הונא Rav Huna from the משנה. Mishna. So now we
need to say, well, whose position is the משנה Mishna to see
whether we should hold like רב נחמן Rav Nachman or like
רב הונא. Rav Huna. Okay. ולימא ליה רבי מאיר היא דאמר אדם
מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם. Veleyma leh Rabbi Meir hi de'amar adam
makneh davar shelo ba la'olam. Ah, but wait a second. So רבי
מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's position across ש"ס Shas is מקנה דבר שלא בא
לעולם. makneh davar shelo ba la'olam. You can sell something which does
not yet exist. Is that what we're talking about here? No. You're
talking about selling something that does exist to a person who doesn't
exist. Ah, so the גמרא Gemara says אימור דשמעת ליה לרבי מאיר
לדבר שישנו בעולם לדבר שאינו בעולם מי שמעת ליה. Eimor dishmat leh
leRabbi Meir ledavar sheyeshno ba'olam ledavar she'eino ba'olam mi shmat leh. So
לדבר, ledavar, selling to a party who doesn't exist, maybe רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir doesn't apply. That is, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is about
transferring ownership of futures in some sense. You can be מקנה דבר
שלא בא לעולם, makneh davar shelo ba la'olam, but not מקנה למי
שלא בא לעולם. makneh lemi shelo ba la'olam.
Right, right. The human being is the future.
Right. What that means is there's no יד yad to make a
קניין. kinyan. If no one is there to acquire the property, then
what meaningful sense... meaning and this is part of the question of
why do we say that according to the תנאים Tannaim who disagree
with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, why does מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם
makneh davar shelo ba la'olam not work? So there's a מחלוקת machlokes
in the ראשונים, Rishonim, whether it's because there's a technical problem, it
fundamentally cannot operate as a קניין kinyan if the object that you're
selling doesn't exist, or is it because
there's no גמירת דעת. gemiras da'as. If it doesn't exist, you don't
have the mental severity of mind to be able to say this
is a real transaction because the property doesn't exist yet.
That מחלוקת machlokes is, for example, if I can be מקנה makneh
you the apples that are going to grow on my tree.
Well, that is even, even other תנאים Tannaim besides רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir agree that
דקל לפירותיו dekel lepeirosov we say more broadly because of a tree
there's an expectation that it will produce fruit. But if it's something
שלא בא לעולם shelo ba la'olam like
whatever diamonds I mine from this mine or something, well, that's something
different, that's a deal, that's a condition. But things like that or
where there may not be any
any... that it could be solved by taking a שבועה shvua along
with the קנין. kinyan. That is, making a קנין kinyan can serve
for the transaction and to demonstrate your acquiescence to that transaction, you
could take a שבועה. shvua. And it pops up of all places,
interestingly enough, in classic אחרוניש achronish style, in the discussion of יעקב
Yaakov buying the בכורה bechora from עשו. Esav. When יעקב Yaakov bought
the בכורה bechora from עשו, Esav, he said, השבעה לי. hishava li.
Swear to me. Why did he say swear to me? Because he
was buying something which had not yet come into existence yet. He
was buying the rights to the ירושה. yerusha. The father was still
alive. So he was buying the rights to collect on the inheritance,
he needed to take a שבועה shvua because it's דבר שלא בא
לעולם. davar shelo ba l'olam. So anyway, so that's a very אחרוניש
achronish read into the פשט pshat there, but we could figure that
out. Okay. So even if you say רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם, adam makneh davar shelo ba l'olam,
maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir does not agree with the principle articulated
by רב נחמן Rav Nachman that an עובר ubar could be זוכה
zocheh to in ownership. Okay. ולימא
ליה
רבי יוסי היא, V'leima leh Rabbi Yose hi, maybe it's רבי יוסי's
Rabbi Yose position דאמר d'amar עובר קני, ubar kani, רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose just very straight says a fetus can acquire property, דתנן d'tnan
based on this משנה, mishnah, עובר פוסל ואינו מאכיל דברי רבי יוסי.
ubar posel v'eino ma'achil divrei Rabbi Yose. So an עובר ubar is
פוסל, posel, that means disqualifies. What are we talking about? We're talking
about a כהניק kohanic family where there are slaves perhaps etc. So
or in this case, what about a woman who is herself a
בת כהן bat kohen who's married to a ישראל, Yisrael, so while
they're married, she cannot eat תרומה. terumah. When her husband dies, she
could go back to eating תרומה, terumah, but if she's pregnant with
the child of a ישראל, Yisrael, with a זר zar fetus, she
could not eat תרומה. terumah. So עובר פוסל, ubar posel, an עובר
ubar prevents someone from being able to eat תרומה terumah in the
case of a בת כהן bat kohen married to a ישראל Yisrael
who then her husband died. ואינו מאכיל, V'eino ma'achil, but in the
case of a זרה, zarah, a non-כהן kohen woman married to a
כהן kohen who became pregnant and then her כהן kohen husband died
and she's pregnant with a male כהן kohen baby or or even
a בת כהן bat kohen baby, if she's pregnant with the fetus,
אינו מאכיל. eino ma'achil. She can't eat תרומה terumah either way, whether
she's a בת ישראל bat Yisrael married to a כהן kohen who's
pregnant or she's a בת כהן bat kohen who was married to
a ישראל Yisrael who's pregnant, either way עובר פוסל ואינו מאכיל דברי
רבי יוסי. ubar posel v'eino ma'achil divrei Rabbi Yose. That is, עובר
קני ubar kani in that the קנין kinyan of the the קנין
kinyan of the עובר ubar is to say that enough is strong
enough to say פוסל. posel. That is, the עובר ubar exists enough
to prevent a בת כהן bat kohen from being able to go
back to her father's house to eat תרומה. terumah.
It's a step from there to קני. kani.
It's a step from there to קני, kani, for sure. It's a
and certainly, the big מחלוקת machloket in כתובות Ketubot and in קידושין
Kiddushin is about whether any of these restrictions about what in which
phase of marriage and which phase in the relationship and pregnancy and
not and all these questions about a בת כהן bat kohen eating
תרומה terumah or a בת ישראל bat Yisrael eating תרומה terumah and
things like that, how much of it is דאורייתא, d'oraita, how much
of it is דרבנן d'rabanan that they were worried maybe she'll go
back to her father's house and they'll pour her a glass of
wine that's תרומה terumah wine and she'll drink it, but not necessarily
that there's any problem דאורייתא, d'oraita, but we're worried that it will
lead to other violations of the תרומה. terumah. Okay. But at least
רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose position עובר פוסל ואינו מאכיל דברי רבי יוסי.
ubar posel v'eino ma'achil divrei Rabbi Yose. So the גמרא Gemara says
שאני ירושה הבאה מאליה. shani yerusha haba'ah me'eleiha. No, ירושה yerusha is
different because ירושה yerusha is automatic. And that's a very interesting contrast
that we have between ירושה yerusha and other kinds of קנינים kinyanim
that usually רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose was talking about a case עובר
קני ubar kani is talking about a case of how this woman
will or will not be allowed to be given תרומה terumah and
to eat the תרומה, terumah, but that's different than ירושה. yerusha. ירושה
yerusha because it's automatic, maybe we would say an עובר ubar actually
has more standing because the עובר ubar is sort of passive, very
passively involved because ירושה yerusha is totally automatic. Okay. Or maybe the
reverse, maybe an עובר ubar is not strong enough presence to be
there to create the context for ירושה yerusha to operate. Either way,
ירושה הבאה מאליה, yerusha haba'ah me'eleiha, ירושה yerusha is different from other
קנינים, kinyanim, so maybe we can't learn from רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose
position. ולימא ליה רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה היא, V'leima leh Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka hi, maybe it's רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה's Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka position, דאמר לא שנא ירושה ולא שנא מתנה. d'amar lo shna
yerusha v'lo shna matana. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka
does not distinguish between ירושה yerusha and giving a gift. That is,
he sees the operative principle at play in giving an inheritance from
the from the deceased
bequeathing it to the heirs is basically fundamentally is just like giving
a gift, is not like a transactional process or it's not automatic,
but is as if an automatic gift but it fundamentally is the
same process דתנן רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר אם אמר על מי
שראוי ליורשו דבריו קיימין
D'tnan Rabi Yohanan ben Beroqa omer
im amar al mi sherauy l'yorsho d'varav kayamim if he spoke about
someone who was suitable to inherit anyway that is talking about a
certain case of שכיב מרע shkhiv mera and things like that then
דבריו קיימין d'varav kayamim that is if you try to stipulate about
the ירושה yerusha in such a way that it would be modified
or changed that's okay you're allowed to make a תנאי tenay on
your ירושה yerusha because it's basically just giving a gift other תנאים
tannaim would disagree and would say oh that's מתנה על מה שכתוב
בתורה matne al ma shekatuv ba'Torah you're trying to create a condition
to modify or change the operative principle of how inheritance works at
the Torah level which would not work
so the argument of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabi Yohanan ben Beroqa
since ירושה's yerusha fundamentally a subset of
מתנה matana you have more control
so you could be מקנה לעובר makneh l'ubar that because
right because it's a מתנה matana and
because it's a מתנה matana and
the bequeathing father is fundamentally in charge of the process of
all giving right so he's able to control it he's able to
create a תנאי tenay he's able to he's in control of that
arena right
it's all optimization because he's right okay
but
still so רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabi Yohanan ben Beroqa is not
so firm why
so דבריו קיימין d'varav kayamim אימור דשמעת ליה לרבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
לדבר שישנו בעולם Emor d'sham'at leh le'Rabi Yohanan ben Beroqa l'davar sheyeshno
ba'olam but maybe רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabi Yohanan ben Beroqa only
applies to giving a gift of something that actually exists so by
giving a gift to someone who is not yet born to a
fetus לדבר שאינו בעולם מי אמר l'davar she'eino ba'olam mi amar whoever
heard of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabi Yohanan ben Beroqa saying you
could give a gift to a fetus ולימא ליה רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא היא וסבר לה כרבי יוסי V'leima leh Rabi Yohanan ben Beroqa
hi v'savar lah k'Rabi Yosi maybe our משנה mishna is authored by
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabi Yohanan ben Beroqa within the position of
רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi so we had רבי מאיר Rabi Meir was
rejected as not strong enough argument רבי יוסי Rabi Yosi was not
strong enough argument רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabi Yohanan ben Beroqa was
not strong enough on his own maybe it's רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
Rabi Yohanan ben Beroqa within רבי
יוסי
Rabi
Yosi
the גמרא Gemara says מי אמר דסבר לה mi amar d'savar lah
whoever heard of such an opinion that רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabi
Yohanan ben Beroqa has to be within רבי יוסי's Rabi Yosi position
okay so ולימא ליה במבשרני V'leima leh b'mevasreni maybe it's like what
we saw already with רבינא Ravina that the משנה mishna is not
talking about any of this the gift is not going to the
עובר ubar the gift is not going to the child the gift
is going to the messenger who brings the father the news that
the child was born ולימא ליה במבשרני אי הכי דקתני סיפא V'leima
leh b'mevasreni i hakhi d'katni seifa but then the סיפא seifa of
the משנה mishna should have should have been written differently what does
the סיפא seifa say ואם אין שם יורש אלא הוא יורש הכל
V'im ein sham yoresh ela hu yoresh hakol that if there is
no other יורש yoresh then this child will inherit all the properties
אי במבשרני יורש מאי עבידתיה Ei b'mevasreni yoresh mai avidteh
and if you're talking about a case of a messenger bringing the
news to the father then what does it have to do with
ירושה yerusha we're not talking about the messenger isn't the יורש yoresh
so the גמרא's Gemara going to continue I'm going to stop here
just to because the flow of it is that the next part
of the סוגיא sugya is very long and I don't want to
eat up all of tomorrow's דף daf but we are in the
middle of this discussion basically the challenge we have here is we
have the מחלוקת machloket between רב הונא Rav Huna and רב נחמן
Rav Nachman רב נחמן Rav Nachman thinks you would be able to
transfer the gift to the עובר ubar רב הונא Rav Huna says
you cannot and we're trying to see is there a way for
רב הונא Rav Huna to defend himself by asserting that the משנה
mishna was a rejected opinion so we first have to identify who
is the תנא tanna of the משנה mishna in order to defend
רב הונא Rav Huna רב הונא Rav Huna
right because that's the הלכה halakha presumably right so
רב הונא Rav Huna and רב הונא Rav Huna generally we פוסקין
poskin like so that's going to be the and just a more
articulated principle המזכה לעובר לא קנה hamizakeh l'ubar lo kana whoever tries
to transfer ownership to a fetus does nothing which is very resonant
for us it makes a lot of sense just sort of at
the gut level that that should be the הלכה halakha
I actually looked up the רמב"ם Rambam okay and it's basically according
to רב הונא Rav Huna except if the fetus is the person's
son
okay so maybe maybe we'll see a more interesting conclusion in the
סוגיא sugya yeah so we'll have to see well I hope everyone
has a wonderful day would you explain
again how